Guide to the James Upson Sanders Papers 1875-1922
Montana Historical Society
James Upson Sanders papers
1875-1922
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 66
Sanders, James U. (James Upson), 1859-1923
.5 linear feet of shelf space
James Sanders (1859-1923) was a Helena, Montana, attorney and librarian of the Montana Historical Society. Papers include general correspondence (1878-1922), writings, and diaries (1875-1888) covering his boyhood, education, travels, and early legal career.
James Upson Sanders was born on July 12, 1859, in Akron, Ohio, the first of five sons of Wilbur Fisk Sanders and Harriet Peck Fenn Sanders. In 1863, the family moved overland to Bannack, Idaho Territory. James Sanders attended public schools in Helena, Montana, and then, in 1878, went with his younger brother Wilbur to Phillips Academy at Exeter, New Hampshire. In 1881, he attended law school at Columbia. After graduating in 1884, he returned to Montana and joined his father's law firm. Sanders practiced law thirty-eight years. Upon his retirement in 1922, Sanders became librarian of the Montana Historical Society. He also served as secretary of the Society of Montana Pioneers for twenty-six years. James U. Sanders died as the result of an automobile accident on April 17, 1923.
This collection consists of correspondence, diaries, and writings of James U. Sanders. The correspondence deals primarily with his historical work and his attempts to publish his father's works. The diaries recount his boyhood in Helena, his education at Phillips and Columbia, his various travels, and his early legal career.
Arranged by series
Collection open for research.
Diary includes a copy of Harriet P. Sanders' diary (1867). Separated from Wilbur Fisk Sanders Papers (MC 53).
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Sanders, James U. (James Upson), 1859-1923
Europe--Description and travel; Helena (Mont.)--Commerce--Attorneys; Helena (Mont.)--Education; Yellowstone National Park--Description and travel
Public schools
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - S.E. Constable; W.J. McConnell, 1914, 1922 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - A.J. Noyes (re subscriptions for proposed history of Montana), 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- Incoming Correspondence
  - A-B (correspondents include J.M. Ashley, A. Bessette), 1886, 1914 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Helen P. Clarke; William A. Clark, 1899, 1917 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - C-F (correspondents include Allen Coffin; C.P. Connolly; J.S. Cushing Company; and L.A. Fenner re trial of George Ives), 1895-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - George Bird Grinnell, 1895-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - G-L (correspondents include O.F. Goddard, J.M. Hannaford, Charles A. Hartman, F. Augustus Heinze, Mrs. A.M. Hough, Richard R. Kilroy, William Lindsay), 1889-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - P-R (correspondents include E.S. Paxson, Martha Edgerton Plassman, Frederick Root), 1915 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - E.P. Sanders, Helen Sanders, S.M. Sanders, 1878-1918 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Reginald Stanley, 1903 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - S-W (correspondents include Granville Stuart, George D. Upson, J.A. Tufts, University of Montana, Lester S. Willson, George Wing, unidentified uncle), 1878-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1886-1922, undated (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Circular letters re publication promotion for W.F. Sanders' papers, 1914 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Wilbur E. Sanders (typescript copies, originals not in collection), 1893 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  - Letters neither to nor from J.U. Sanders, 1928, 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
- Diaries
  - Books No. 1-6, 8 (No. 6 includes Harriet Sanders' diary, 1867), 1875-1876, 1879-1881 (Box-folder 1 / 16-19)
  - Books No. 9-11, 1881-1884 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
  - Un-numbered diaries, 1884-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 4-5)
- Legal Documents
  - Agreement with A.J. Noyes to raise subscription for publication of Wilbur Fisk Sanders' papers, 1914 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
- Writings
  - "Contest of Edwards vs. Langford" (re first Idaho legislature; "Rose's Grave" (re Edward Rose); "The Bannack Lobby"; "3-7-77" (re vigilantes); "Montana's First Map"; untitled (re last Chance Gulch); untitled (re Bannack); "The Dignity of the Presidential Office", 1912-1919, undated (Box-folder 2 / 7)
- Miscellany
  - Invitation to reception of First Regiment of Montana Voluntary Infantry, 1899 (Box-folder 2 / 8)